Okay, so today we start Greek civilization.
好的，今天我们开始讲希腊文明。
And it is incredible what Greek civilization is.
好的，希腊文明很精彩！
It is the greatest, most creative,
most significant civilization ever in human history.
最重要的...
The Greeks really created Western civilization.
...
And not only were the Greeks the greatest civilization,
there's really not been a second great civilization.
还有一段时间没有出现第二大文明。
So let's think about how incredible the Greeks were.
让我们来想想希腊的精彩之处！
If you look at literature,
如果你看得很久的书！
the Greeks basically created literature with Homer.
希腊基本上用荷马创作了文学。
Homer wrote two books called the Iliad
荷马写了两本书，叫作…
and the Odyssey.
“……………”
And he wrote these books about 3,000 years ago.
他在三千年前写下这些书。
Now last year I taught the great books to the students.
去年我给学生们上过这本大作。
And we read many books.
我们读了多本书。
And by far their favorite book was the Iliad.
Okay, so think about this, how a Greek writer writing 3,000 years ago for a Greek audience,
...
his book still resonates, still impresses,
and still impresses students in China today.
他在三千年前写下这些书。
Okay, so that's Homer.
他在三千百里?
Then you have Plato, philosophy, Plato.
这句...??
And even today, you have Plato. Just, even today, there are many who considered Plato
翻译1
the greatest philosopher, who ever lived,
翻译2
there are many people who read, The Republic,
翻译中...
by Plato, and they, and they, say, it, transforms,
their, lives, okay, it, makes, them, think, very, differently, about, the, world,
翻译1
then, you, have, in, history, a, man, named,,,,
...
If, you, are, a, military,
如果你是军人，今天读...
leader, today, you, read,,, read Thucydides, okay?
如果...
There are still many generals today in America,
在美洲里有许多士兵…
in Russia, in Europe, who
]}
believe reading Thucydides will help them win wars.
...
Okay, so not only the Greeks create civilization,
but their works, their books,
但...??
are still widely read today,
?
and considered amazing,
36: 1/2? 1/2? 1/JSON? JSON? 1/?? 1/??? ???????
okay? So now the question I have is,
]}We need to translate cues [36] and [37] into Simplified Chinese. The cues are: [36] and considered amazing, [37] okay? So now the question I have? Wait the cue text: [36] and considered amazing, [37] okay? So now the question I have is,{
how did this happen?
如何回到?
How were the Greeks able to create humanity's greatest civilization?
???????????????????????????????????????????????????????????翻??????????????????????????????????????翻???????????????…
In really about 200 years, okay?
大约200年左右，
They really were not dominant for a long time.
它们在很久的时间里才算得上去！
They really created all these works in about 200 years altogether.
在大约200年之内，
So how is this possible?
Okay, so let's go back to the Greek history.
好的，回到古希腔?
Let's go back to the last class. We talked about the Bronze Age collapse, right?
好的，回到古希?????????
And we talked about how, in about 1200 BCE,
Greece was united in a place called Mycenaean Greece,
okay? So basically the Mycenaeans controlled Greece, and Greece was the monarchy.
]}We need to translate cue [48]into Simplified Chinese. The cue:
And it was no different from any other place in the world.
And it was no different fromany other place in the world.
At this point, 1200 BCE, the world was basically the same.
At this...???
Okay? And then the society collapsed, and the world was the same.
because of the Bronze Age collapse.
因为金属时代的崩溃…
And three things happened, okay? First of all, centralization.
...
The idea that you had a unified society,
统一的社会的想法，随后就消失了，随后又是…
it went away, okay? So Greece became chaotic and decentralized.
统一的...
That's the first thing that happened. Same thing that
那是第一件事，…
happened is Greece became illiterate.
...
So the Greeks lost the ability to read and write.
所以希腊人失去读写能力。
We call this the Dark Ages.
我们把它叫作…
So from about 1000 to about 600 BCE,
从大约公元前1000年到大约公元前600年，但在这400年里，希腊人基本上能读写。
but for 400 years, the Greeks basically lost the ability to read and write.
从大约公元前1000年到大约公元前600年，但这400年里，希腊人基本能读写。
We call this the Dark Ages because
我们把它叫作“暗黑时代”因为…
we don't have any books or writing from that period.
我们把它…
It's completely dark to us, okay?
它完全是个空白的时光，…
So the second thing that happened, the Greeks became illiterate.
...
The third thing that happened is the Greeks became poor.
第66条：希腊人变得贫穷。
Okay, so before the Greeks traded with the world, it was very prosperous,
第67条：希腊人先前与之相互交流，先前…
and then, because of the Bronze Age collapse,
第68条：…
it started to become more isolated, and
it ... …
it became a lot poorer, okay, so these are the three major consequences
?
of the Bronze Age collapse in Greece, it became decentralized,
…
it became illiterate, it became poor, and
...
the amazing thing is,
it's because of these three things
...
that Greece became the most creative civilization,
那时，希腊里…
civilization in the world
?………?
Okay, so remember this it is because
………..??……..
of the destruction of old Greece It's
旧希腊里毁灭的结果是
because Greece became chaotic illiterate and poor that Greece
因为希腊里变得混乱、文盲、贫穷，最终成为世界上最文明的国家。
eventually became The most civilized the greatest civilization in the world.
最终成为世界最有文明的。”
Okay, so let me explain how this happened
OK?…?????????????????????????????
Okay, so there are three major reasons
OK?…??……???…??????…???…??…??…???
Why Greek civilization became dominant?
OK………..??…..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..???
The first reason is the polis
第一个原因是多伦里
the polis It's hard for us to translate it.
...
We usually translate it as city -state.
Okay, a City state
OK?……...??…...??…??………??……??………??………??…………………??………..??…..??…..??…..???…..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..???…..??..??..t…..??..t…..t…..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..??t…..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..??t…..t…..t..t..…..t..t..t..t..t..t..??…..t…..t…..t…..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t…????????...????????..?????..????????..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..OK???…??..???…..??..
And this is where we get the word politics, but really
...
What it means is community
翻译成中文
Community And
社区与
the idea of the polis is a
??
community of people who discuss
人们讨论的社区
politics together
How how to best run the town?
94. 该如何最好的运行城镇？
Okay, and because
95. 先前的句子??
of this chaos there were thousands of policies around Greece
这个混乱中有数千个城邦，分布在希腓各地
Of about a thousand people each.
大约一千人组成的城邦
Okay, so it's a very small community and
好的，所以它是一个很小的社区，并且它成为希腓社会的主要政治结构。
This became the main political structure of Greek society.
好的，接着说，是个小型的社区。”
Okay, so the polis is one factor second factor that happened is the
???
alphabet So
]}We need to translate cues 100and 101. Let's read them: [100]
after the Greeks became illiterate they had to relearn literacy Okay,
...
they had to relearn how to read and write in the process.
They adopted a new writing system called the alphabet
???
Okay, which forever transformed a society
...
The last thing is Homer
Homer was a poet who
Homer was a poetwho
introduced to the Greek a new way of imagining the world Okay
...
So, these are the three major factors that led to the rise of Greek civilization,
and if you look at each factor Okay, so the polis, was a political
??
revolution revolution revolution revolution
...
revolution revolution revolution
revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution revolution with each other. And
革命革命革命革命革命革命革命革命革命革命革命革命革命与每一次相互。然后Homer是个真正的知识革命。
Homer was really an intellectual revolution.
革命…
It forever transformed how Greeks saw and
???
imagined the world around them.
]}
Okay? So
好的，...
let's go over each
...
of these revolutions one by one.
??
Okay? So, the polis.
...
There were three things about the polis
??
that allowed for innovation
...
and creativity in Greece.
Okay? The first thing about the polis was competition.
好的？多谢...
Okay? These polises were all spread out
好的？这些城邦都分散在各处
and they were all competing against each other for resources.
并且各自竞争着去争夺资源。
They were constantly at war with each other and that
他们在不断的相互相互...
allowed for massive innovation.
...
Okay? And again, remember, there's no centralized authority now.
好的？再说一次，...
Okay? So, there's no centralized authority now. There's no centralized authority now. That's the first thing.
好的...
Second thing is diversity.
第二点是多样性。
So, if you look at a map of Greece,
“我”??????????????????????????????????????????
Greece has very diverse geography.
希腊有着多样的地理。
Okay? It has farmland, it has mountains,
...
it has plains, it has coastal land.
它有平原，...
Okay? And depending on where
它有平原...
you were geographically in Greece,
你在地理上位于希腊。
you develop a different equation.
...
Okay? So, you have a map of Greece, you have a map of Greece, you have a map of Greece, you have a map of Greece, you have the economy and culture and society
based on the geography. Okay?
基于地理。好？
Does that make sense? And so, you add on diversity.
这有道理吗？于是你再加上多样性。
And the last factor was the idea of democracy.
最后一个因素是民主的概念。
Okay? So, Greek civilization
好的？所以，希腊文明
introduced the idea of democracy or the modern sense of democracy to us.
好的，回到…
And the reason why is, at this time, Greece was very poor.
...
Okay? If you're very poor Or you need everyone to participate
好的？如果你很贫穷，或者你需要大家参与并努力工作，尤其是在与其他城邦作战时。
and work hard,
好的，...】}We need to produce JSON with translations array of 3 items? Wait cues 146-148: 3 cues. Provide translations accordingly. Need to translate each cue. Let's translate. Cue 146:
especially in battles against other polices.
? Actually cue 146:
So the rule was, you could be rich or poor,
??
but if you fought for us, you had the right to speak.
You could be the leader of this polis,
??
and you had the right to speak, but you could be the poorest person in this polis,
在这场战斗中，你可以是富有也可以是贫穷，只要能为我方作战。”
and you still had the right to speak because
你可以在此城邦里担任领袖。”
everyone had a responsibility to defend the polis.
在此城邦里，若能为我方作战，便可发声。”
So this introduced the idea of democracy.
在此引入了民主的概念。
And what this meant was that
这回归了其回归回归...
everyone basically had to participate politically.
其回归…
So you could be a farmer, but you still had to think about the political life,
在这场战斗中，你可以是个农夫，但仍然要考虑政治生活。
and you still had a responsibility to speak up in front of your peers.
在此处，若能在此城邦里…
And this is where we get the idea of polis from.
...
And this was a major driver of innovation in Greece.
并且...
So does this make sense, guys, the polis?
...
Any questions so far? We might move on.
So one of the major innovations of the polis
在这场战斗…
was the introduction of the
在此…
alphabet into Greek society.
...
So let me explain the development of writing systems
让我来解释一下文字系统的发展历程。
over time to you.
再接着说…
And this is going to be a bit complicated,
…
so make sure you're following along.
在欧洲先行先发地发展了文字。
If I'm saying something unclear to you, make sure you interrupt and ask me questions.
]}We need to translate cues 170-172. Provide translations array with 3 strings. Ensure Chinese natural. Use line breaks if needed. Let's craft. 170:
So writing was first developed in Europe,
]} seems wrong. We need translation. 170:
in Western society, in Egypt and in Samaria.
??
And they did so to support the development of the alphabet in the Middle Ages.
...
to solve an economic problem. So
these societies were very wealthy, and they needed people,
这些社会非常富裕，他们需要人来做农夫，帮助他们建路。
farmers, to help them build roads and
...
build irrigation networks and build temples.
建造灌溝網絡與建造神廟。
To do so, I need to pay these workers.
為了完成此事，我要付給這些工人。
So writing system became a contract.
写字系统成为合同。
So basically, the writing system,
写字系统的基本是...
at first, was a pictogram, a pictograph,
先前是一个图形，图画，
that served the function of a contract.
先前…
So for example, if I do this,
...
okay, two people, okay?
So what this is saying is, if you work for me,
好的，...
I promise to give two people two bushels of wheat,
...
okay? And so when you have this, you can then
好的？当你拿到这个后，你可以把它交给我，我就会把麦子给你。
give it to me, and I have to give you the wheat.
我把给你们的那份麦子给了。”】}We need to translate cues 188-190. Provide array of 3 translations. Ensure Chinese natural. Let's craft. 188:
Does that make sense? So it first started out, I have to give you the wheat.
Actually cue 188:
So it started out as pictograms. And what they recognized is, hey,
它最初以象形文字出现，随后他们发现它可以是个符号。
we can just have this as symbols.
我们可以把它当作符号来使用。
So maybe just two faces and then two Vs.
也许只要两张脸，后面两张“V”字形。
And this could represent the same thing.
这可以代表同样东西。
Because everyone understood what it meant.
因为大家都明白它的意思。
So you went to symbolism. That's the next step.
于是你进入符号化。下一步。
But then what they recognized is,
hey, these symbols can also represent ideas.
...
Okay, so here's an example.
All right, so you have maybe a sun
All 好 好 好 ...
and a moon, right?
...
Okay, sun and moon. They can represent the sun
好的，太阳与月亮。它们可以代表太阳
and the moon, but if you put them together, okay,
好的，太阳与…
sun and the moon, you get the concept of day,
太阳与月亮，你能得到白天的概念吗？
right?
太阳与月亮，能得到白天概念吗？
So now you have a concept, an idea, day, okay?
现在有了一个概念，好的？
We call this an ideogram.
我们把它叫做…
And guess what, guys? Chinese is an ideogramic term.
好的，...
It's a language. Does that make sense?
...
Okay, and then as they continued developing writing,
好的，接着写作...
they recognized that, you know what?
好的，写作...
It would be a lot easier for
212. 译文
us to communicate if these ideograms represented syllables
213. 译汉
and sounds instead.
213. ??
Okay? So rather than representing ideas,
好的？于是...
let's get them to represent sounds.
...
So for example, this is sun, right?
And this is moon. Well,
和这就是月亮。好吧，
now if we do this,
现在如果我们把它做成…
it becomes moon, sun, right?
其后变成了…
Which is the English word for monsoon, which means storm.
哪一个是英文单词“monsoon”，意思是“风暴”
Okay? So
好的，先把它写成“monsoon”
now this tells us to read it as monsoon.
现在把它们写成“风暴”
Okay? And then
...
the final recognition is, guess what?
翻译1
We can actually just have
翻译后”...??……???…????????……??…???……??………??………??………??………??……?????…???……??……???……??……??……?????………??………??………??………1?……..???…..?…..??…..?…..??…..?…??…..??…..??……………………………………………………
the sound represent a consonant,
音符代表一个辅音，
okay? The simplest sound.
好的？最简洁的音节。
And this would be an M, this would be an S.
??
So if I write something like this, it now becomes SM,
翻译后…………..??…..??…..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..???…..??..??..??....??..??..??..??..??....??..??..??..??..??..??..????…?????..??..??....……??…..??..??..??..??..??..???…..??..??..t…..??..??..t…..??..t…..t…..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..??t???..t?..t..t..t..t..t..t..??..t…..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..??..t....t..........??…..t…..t…..t…..t..t..t..t..t..t..t..??..t…..t..t..t..t..t..
or sum. Okay?
??
And we call this the alphabet.
...
Does that make sense? Okay?
??
So this is the development of writing.
...
And the reason why we do this is,
with each innovation, with each development,
翻译后…………………………………………………………………………………
we're allowed more flexibility in our language to communicate our ideas.
我们可以在语言里更灵活地表达我们的想法。
Does that make sense, guys?
好吧，大家好？
Okay? So now with the alphabet,
好的？现在有了字母表，发生了大事！
something remarkable has happened.
好的，字母表出现后，有了可见的字母表！
Before these different stages
在这几种不同的写作阶段之前
of writing required a professional class of people to manage the writing system.
在这几种不同的前后??
Okay? We call these scribes, right?
好的？我们叫它们为书写者，对吗？
Scribes. The reason why is that
写字写字??
writing is not speaking.
写作不是说话。
Speaking is one language, but writing is a different language.
说话是个别的语句？
This is true for Chinese, right?
这件事在中文里很久…
Well, it was true back then as well.
...
So to learn to read and write,
好的，读写能写作…
you had to have professional scribes to do so,
...
because it was such a complicated task.
Okay? Does that make sense?
Okay? Does thatmake sense?
All right? But
...
now with the alphabet,
writing can become speaking.
写作可以变成说话。
And this marked an incredible revolution
而且此时又出现了一个极大变革。
in human thought, in the capacity to think.
在人类思维的里程里，能写作的写作。”
Okay? So let me explain why.
好的？那就让我来解释一下。
Before the invention of writing, we lived in an oral culture.
在写作之前，先前先前先前先前先前先前先前先前先前先前先前
Okay? An oral culture means we don't write,
好的，先前先前…
we just speak to each other. All right?
我们刚刚才说话。好吧？
Now we live in a writing culture, a literary culture,
现在我们在写作文化里，文学文化里，才有写作。
where we don't actually speak to each other, we mainly just write to each other.
在写作里…
Okay? So mainly through email or texting.
好的？主要通过邮件或短信。
Okay? Now, there are certain advantages
好的？现在有某些优势
to both cultures.
好的，咱们先前…
With oral culture, the first major advantage is
带有口头文化，首个大优势是
it's very emotional.
它是很有情绪的
Okay? When I'm speaking to you, I'm trying to get you excited.
好的？我正好说给你们…
I'm trying to get you to pay attention. So I'm trying to think about how to rouse your emotions.
我正试着让你们专注。先前…
So oral culture, it's very emotional focus.
口口…
That's the first major advantage.
先前…
Second major advantage is it's very innovative
第二个大优势是它非常创新
and open. And what this means is
第二个大优势是…
I can create words when I speak.
...
Right? I can say, Okay?
右？我能说，好的？
That means nothing.
那………………
Okay? But I can create it and when we're speaking, you can figure out what I mean.
好的………………
So when I'm speaking, I can create all these different words.
当我说话时，我可以创造出这些不同的词语。
So there's room for innovation
于是有了创新的空间
and imagination in oral culture.
以及口头文化中的想象力。
Does that make sense? Okay?
...
The third thing is
第三件事是
the thing about oral culture is it forces
口语文化的事物是……
everyone to have a really strong memory.
每个人都要有很强的记忆力。
The reason why is when I speak, I have to remember my speech.
当我说话时，我要记住我的语句。
Right? And then you have to remember my speech in order to respond to my speech.
右？然后你得记住我的话才能回应我的话。
And these speeches go on for like hours and hours.
这些话语持续了好几小时。
So back then, during oral culture,
所以回到口语文化时期，每个人都有相机式记忆力。
everyone had a photographic memory.
Okay? Does that make sense? So back then,
好的？这有道理吗？于是回到...
they were a lot smarter than we are today.
他们在此时...
And it's the same as, remember,
和…相同，记得是…
during the hunter -gatherer stage, right?
在………
When we're out in the field, guess what, guys?
当时我们在外面…??…????
They were a lot stronger, faster,
当时…??…????
and healthier than we are today.
和…更健康。
Because today, all we do is sit around.
因为今天…
Right? Does that make sense? So back then, they were a lot smarter than us.
好的，...
So these are the three major advantages of oral culture.
这些是口语文化的三大优势。
It's a very emotional language. It's very innovative.
它是一种很有情感的语言。
And it forces you to have a really strong memory.
它的强大记忆力要求很高。
Okay? But
好的？ 但…
there's also a lot of advantages to writing culture as well that oral culture doesn't have.
有点儿…
So for example, the first major advantage is rather than emotional, it has to be logical.
好的，...
Right? It has to make sense by itself.
...
I can't trick you with rhetoric.
我能用语法...
All right? I have to use reason and
...
logic to persuade you because
逻辑能让你说…
you can read it at your own time.
我可…
Okay? So that's the first major advantage.
好的？所以这就是第一个主要优势。
Second major advantage is it's very disciplined.
第二个主要优势是它很有纪律性。
Okay? Meaning, okay, I can't make up words.
好的？意思是，我没能造词。
I have to use words we agree on.
好的，...
Okay? The third major advantage is
OK? 第三...??
even though it decreases my memory,
...
it stores up brain space for me to think deeply about the argument,
翻译1
for me to reflect on your argument
翻译2
and find logical problems
和...…
in your argument. Okay? Does that make sense?
...
All right? So we are basically,
好的？所以我们基本上，
before they were in oral culture,
在前面我们先是口语文化，
and that has its advantages.
并且有它的优势。
Now we are in a literary culture and we've lost the oral culture.
现在我们已进入文学文化，失去了口语文化。
But when the Greeks discovered the alphabet,
当希腊发现字母表时，
what happened was they combined the advantages of both cultures.
其后又把两种文化的优势结合起来。
Okay? They were, most of the time, they were speaking,
好的？他们大多数时间里说着，他们在口语文化里生活，却又有机会把它们写下来。
they were living in oral culture, but
好的，先前的口语里，先前口语里！
they also had the opportunity to write down their thoughts.
先前口语里…
Which allowed them the advantages of the literary culture.
哪能让他们拥有文学文化的优势。
To have a more disciplined,
有点儿…
focused, logical mind.
有点…
Okay? Does that make sense? And
好的？那有道理吗？
this marked an incredible revolution in the capacity for human beings to think.
这标志着人类思维能力的极大变革。
Okay? Any questions so far? Okay?
好的，先前…
This is a very complicated concept. I want to make sure you're following along.
这是一种非常复杂的概念。以便我能把它写成一条好句子。”
Okay? Any questions about what I just said?
...
Before I move on? All right.
Now, let's move on to Homer.
...
Okay? Homer. So,
we discussed the polis and how it is a new political structure
...
which allows for freedom and democracy.
允许自由与民主的结构。
We discussed the alphabet, which
我们先前的字母表，先前的字母表...
marks a revolution in our capacity to think.
先前的字母字母...
Okay? Now it comes along, Homer.
好的，先前...??
And Homer is, is a man who is a poet.
??????????????????????????????????????????????…
And back then, there were many poets who went around and told stories
]}We need to translate cues 345-347. Provide JSON array translations. Let's translate each cue. Ensure Chinese natural. Use line breaks if needed. Let's produce translations. 345:
about the world. Okay?
关于世界。好吗？
Legends, mythologies.
传说，神话。
And the very best poets are usually hired by kings.
而最优秀的诗人通常被国王雇佣。
Okay? Rich people. Because kings need poets to solve three problems.
好的？王国需要诗人来解决三件事。
Okay? Kings usually hire poets to solve three problems.
We need to translate cue 352.
The first problem is
...
legitimate authority. Okay? What this means is,
合法的权威。好吧？这就是...
you have to answer the question if you're king, why are you king?
...
Now, we know that most kings get power
现在，大家知道了！
by killing a lot of people.
??
Okay? That's how they become king. By fighting wars and by winning wars.
好的？他们通过打仗和赢仗来成为王。
So, when they become king, they need to clean up their image.
好的，回到！
Okay? They need to legitimize their authority.
好的，...
So, what they tell people is usually what?
...
Why am I king? Why?
我为什么是王？为什么？
Because I, I,
]}
I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I, I,
翻译1
I, I, I,
...
I, I,
我...我...
I, Because there's a poet who sings a beautiful song about me.
And this song can only come from divine inspiration,
我...我...
right?
The poet is a
诗人是个
vessel for divine messages,
翻译1
right? Does that make sense? This poem, this song is
我...我...
so beautiful, it must be divine.
]}{
And if this divine song is saying,
?
I am born of a god,
我出生于神祈
the gods want me to become king, then I must be divine myself.
我想要把...
Does that make sense? Okay?
...
So it's the first major function of poets in the society,
所以这是诗人在社会中的第一个主要功能，是使其成为合法的。”
to legitimize authority.
第二个功能是把…
Second function is to create a cultural identity.
So, you know, in China you have books like San Guanyin, okay?
381. 译文1
Romans of Three Kingdoms.
382. 译语1
You have the Bible. All these literary works,
]}
the function is to create a common culture, a cultural identity,
okay? It tells us what it means to be Chinese.
好的？它告诉我们什么是做为中国人的意义。
Does that make sense? Because then you unify the people
??
who then obey the king, who unifies them, right?
谁又服从王，谁又统一他们，对吧？
That's the second function. The third function is the idea of cultural differentiation.
那是第二个功能。第三个功能是文化差异的概念。
To know who you are, you must also know who you are not.
要知道你们的...
We're Chinese, so therefore we are not Japanese.
...
We're not Korean. We're not American.
??
Okay? Does that make sense? So most literary works
that we have
我们有...
were sponsored by leaders, kings,
to solve these three problems, okay?
395: 1行 1句? 先后? 1..?? 先后??
So in the future we will read the Iliad,
]}
which is what the Romans had.
哪一款罗马人所拥有的那一款
We'll read the Bible, okay?
我们会读《福音》
In China you have like the Romans of the Three Kingdoms.
在中国，你们有像三国时期的罗马人那样的存在。
And all these literary works were
而这些文学作品都已被设计成...
designed to serve the powers
为了服务于...
that exist at that time, okay?
We have...??
Does that make sense? The problem with Homer is
when he was around, and we don't know actually
?
when he was alive, maybe about 800 to 600 BC,
当他在世时，大约公元前800年至公元前600年，
okay? Around then. We don't actually know, okay?
好的，~
But there was no king.
但有一个人…
There was no one to pay him.
...
Therefore he could only make his living
因此他只能靠向周围的人们诉求来谋生
by appealing to the people around him, okay?
再来，给我点儿…
He had to appeal to ordinary people.
...
And so the question then is, if you're a poet,
how do you get ordinary people, who are poor, to pay you money?
怎样给普通人，没事儿的那点儿…
Why would they want to pay you to sing songs for them, okay?
怎样给…
Well, there are three reasons. The first is just entertainment.
好的，先说三点：第一点是娱乐。
Today we listen to songs, we go to movies.
今天我们听歌、去看电影。
Well, back then, their entertainment,
好的，先前往回到…
their source of entertainment was to pay people like Homer
好的，前回…
to sing songs to them, okay?
...
That was what they thought was fun to do.
那时他们认为这很有趣。
That was their source of entertainment. Second reason is education.
那是他们的娱乐来源。第二个原因是学习。
So remember that back then Greece was poor.
于是就这样，回到那时的古希腔。
They didn't have schools. But because of the Polish system,
他们没有学校。因为…
they had to speak in front of their peers.
...
So how did you learn to speak well?
Well, you do so by imitating people
好的，先前…
who do speak well, who are usually poets, right?
...
So when you listen to Homer speak and
give speeches, you can imitate him and
...
copy what he does to make your own speech in front of the people around you.
复制他所做的，来做自己的语句，跟随吧！
In front of your peers, okay?
复制 … … ...
So second reason is educational.
好的，第二个原因是…
Basically, Homer was a teacher as well as a poet,
好的…
okay?
好吧？
And the third reason, and what made Homer special,
可归一百里…
is what we call edification. Edification.
翻译1
Edification means to be a better you,
?
to be a higher you, okay?
...?????????????…
And edification, the way that Homer accomplished edification
...????…
is by changing the way
翻译1
that you saw the world around you,
翻译后
the way you felt about the world, the way you imagined the world, okay?
你对世界的感受，想象的方式，好的？
So let me explain how he did so.
让我来解释一下他怎么做的吧。
But first of all, before I continue, are there any questions about this so far?
先把先前的事说完，先说一段先前的句子。
Anything you are not clear about?
...
Anything I've said that you are not clear about or you're confused by?
Before I continue. Okay,
先把先前的事说完，先说一段先前的句子。
so Homer was a poet who told stories.
先前的那位古希腔诗人，作了个别名的“古”古……
And the most popular story at that time was something called the Trojan War.
先前……
So the main story of the Trojan War is this, okay?
所以特洛伊战争的主线就是这样，好的？
So there was a Greek goddess named Nemesis.
于是有一位希腔女神叫尼米斯。
And Nemesis likes to create problems.
而尼米斯喜欢发起事物。
She's always thinking of ways to get the gods to fight against each other.
她总是想方去让神们互相争斗。
So one day she creates this apple.
...
It's a golden apple. And the golden apple says,
…
to the most beautiful goddess in the world, okay?
到世界最美的女神，好的？
It doesn't say who, it just says, to the most beautiful goddess in the world.
它只给了“到世界最美的女神”一句话。
And then she just puts it on Mount Olympus for the gods to find.
而后把它放在奥林匹斯山上。”
Three goddesses find this apple, and they fight over it, okay?
三位女神发现这枚苹果，随后争夺它，好吗？
The first goddess is Hera, who
第一位女神是希尔拉，...
is the queen god, okay?
第二位女句...
Second goddess is Athena,
第二位女神是雅典娜，
who is the goddess of wisdom.
她是智慧女神。
And the third goddess is Aphrodite, who is the goddess of love.
第三位女神是阿佛尔特，...
They're fighting over this apple all the time.
他们一直在争夺这枚苹果。
And they're creating a huge ruckus.
他们在打闹。
And so the king god, Zeus,
他在把...??
gets tired of all their fighting, and
gets tired of alltheir fighting, and
he finds a human stupid enough to be the judge, okay?
...
So this human, his name is Paris,
his job is to pick who is the most beautiful goddess
他的工作是挑选宇宙中最美的女神，好的？是赫拉、雅典娜还是阿佛尔？
in the universe, okay? Is it going to be Hera, Athena, or Aphrodite, okay?
他的工作是挑选宇宙里最美的女神，好的！】】}We need to translate cues 471-473. Provide JSON array translations. Ensure each string corresponds to each cue. UseChinese terms: 赫拉, 雅典娜, 阿佛尔? Actually Aphrodite is 阿佛洛狄? Wait Chinese: 阿佛洛狄? Usually 阿佛洛狄? But we can use 阿佛洛狄? Let's use 阿佛洛狄? But maybe
And again, he's stupid enough to want to piss off two goddesses, right?
. Let's producetranslations: 471:
So when he's making his decision,
...
all the goddesses try to bribe Paris.
Paris says to Paris, Paris,
...
if you pick me, I will give you your own kingdom.
如果你挑选我，我会把自己的王国给你。
I will make you king of the world.
我会让你成为世界之王。
Paris is like, oh, that's pretty good.
帕里斯说：哦，这倒是不错。
Athena says to Paris,
雅典对帕里斯说：
I will make you the wisest man in the world.
我会让你成为世界上最聪明的人。
I will give you all the knowledge of the world.
我会把世界的全部知识交给你。
And Paris is like, oh, that's pretty good.
帕里斯说：哦，这倒是不错。
And then Aphrodite says, hey,
阿佛德里特说：嗨，...
I will give you the most beautiful woman in the world to marry.
帕里必得...
And then Paris is like, I want that, okay?
翻译1
And so, Paris, but
翻译后续...
the problem is, the most beautiful woman in the world is Helen,
?
queen of Sparta.
公主的帕里斯
She's a Greek who's married to a Greek king.
公主的帕里繁
Paris steals Helen, takes her back to Troy,
公主的帕帕
and then the Greeks get angry, and they raise this huge army.
和随后希腊人愤怒，举起这支庞大军队。
And for 10 years, they attack Troy, which is a walled city, okay?
又在十年里，希腊人攻打古城，古城有墙。
And the war ends when a Greek general named Odysseus,
…
he comes up with this plan.
他提出了这个计划。
He has this idea called the wooden horse, okay?
他有这个想法，叫作木制的木制。
So the Greeks pretend they give up.
...
They're going to go home because they're homesick.
他们回家去，因为他们想家。
And as a present to the Trojans,
作为给给的礼物，...
they leave behind a wooden horse. The Trojans take the wooden horse into the city.
...
At night, the Greeks jump out of the wooden horse,
夜间，希腊人从木制的木制中跳出来，打开门，给回归的回归。
open the gates, and the Trojans are slaughtered, okay?
夜间...
And this is the story of the Trojan War.
And the Greeks love this story,
和希腊人喜欢这故事，
because it's really the Greeks being heroes, right?
因为它们是希腊人…
The Greeks have this great victory.
...
People love to win battles. What's amazing about Homer's story,
人们喜欢赢得战斗。Homers故事中有个惊人之处，
okay? It's called the Iliad, and we'll read this next semester.
ok? 先后??
But there are three things that
??
Homer does in the Iliad
Homer在《伊索》里所作的事
that's really never been done before, okay?
那种事情在前面没做过，没错吗？
And so, with the Iliad, we have the invention of literature.
于是以此为例，先后??
The first thing,
第一件事，
that Homer does is,
他在此处的写作是：
rather than telling the story from the Greek side,
he tells the story from both the Greek and Trojan side.
516. 他从两种方位里写作。
In fact, when you read the Iliad, you'll discover that
516. 只给……??…???
the Trojans are actually more heroic,
?
more courageous, and more brave than the Greeks.
516. 516...
Okay? That's pretty amazing.
好的？这真是太棒了。
And by switching perspectives,
]}We need to translate cues [520] and [521] into Simplified Chinese. We haveprevious translations for [520] maybe? Wait we have previous context: [520]
a new idea comes into being
一个新概念出现了
that never really existed before.
它们的出现…
And we call this idea empathy. Okay?
译文1
Empathy. The ability to see the world from the perspective of other people.
译前
And before, in human civilization,
在前人类文明中，
this didn't really exist before, okay?
在前人类文明中...
But Homer creates this for the Iliad.
但凡尔·马尔...
The second thing that
...
is new and
是的，
unique to the Iliad is human psychology.
是的...
So, for the first time,
...
Homer discusses what motivates
the characters in the Iliad,
在 里尔里...
okay? Why are you fighting this war?
...
And so, the story is between two individuals,
Achilles and King Priam.
阿基琼与王子甲姆
Okay? So, Achilles is the greatest warrior
好的，阿基琼是希腊的最强士兵！
of the Greeks.
Priam is the king of the Trojans.
普里亚姆是特洛伊人的国王。
And they hate each other, okay?
他们相互仇，好的？
Because they're enemies. Achilles is trying to kill Priam.
因为他们是敌人。阿基琼正要去打死普里亚姆。
Priam is trying to defend his family and his home.
普里亚姆正试图守护家人和家园。
So, the Iliad starts like this.
“伊利亚德”从此开始。
Achilles, at the beginning,
阿基琼在开头时，
gets in a fight with Agamemnon, who is the king of the Greeks, okay?
我在此刻把他放进了！
They get in a fight. And they curse each other.
我在此刻………………
And Achilles says, You're a dog, Agamemnon.
先前…………外……??
I'm never going to fight for you again.
我再也不为你而战了。
And Agamemnon, the king, says, I don't need you, man.
阿格玛诺斯王说：我不需要你了。
So, Achilles refuses to fight, okay?
于是阿基琼不再去战斗。
The problem is, Achilles is the greatest warrior
翻译1
of the Greeks. And the Trojans,
翻译2
led by Hector, who is a son of Priam,
翻译?
he sees an opportunity because Achilles refuses to fight.
他看到机会，因为阿基琼不战斗。
And Hector leads the Trojan army out of Troy.
赫克托尔带领土耳兵士兵士兵士兵士兵士兵士兵士兵士兵士兵士
And they're destroying the Greeks.
他人们的士兵士士士士士士士士士士士士士士士士
And the Trojans are about to crush the Greek army.
And the Trojans are aboutto crush the Greek army.
So, the Greek generals say to Agamemnon,
So ... ... ... ...... ... ... ... ...
Could you please beg Achilles to return to the battlefield?
...
And they go and they talk to Achilles.
他在说：...
And Achilles basically says, Screw off.
...
I'm not helping you guys, okay? His friend,
我不再帮你们了，好吗？他朋友，帕特罗克斯？
Patroclus, okay?
我不再给他人们…
Patroclus is basically like his younger brother.
...
He feels sorry for the Greeks, so he pretends to be Achilles
]?
and goes off to battle against Hector.
他去战斗…
Hector kills Patroclus and this angers Achilles, okay?
Hector kills Patroclus andthis angers Achilles, okay?
Achilles is so angry that he jumps into the battle and he kills Hector.
Achilles is so angry that he jumpsinto the battle and he kills Hector.
Once he kills Hector, he does something very odd, okay?
Usually, when you kill someone's body, you return
...
that body to your enemy for a ransom.
Because the belief back then is,
因为当时的信念是，
only if you bury your dead can
因为只要把...
the dead find peace in the afterworld, okay?
死亡者在来世中找到安宁，好吗？
But Achilles is so angry at Hector that
但...
he's torturing Hector's body, which
他在给...
is torturing Priam.
...
But even after Achilles does this,
he can't sleep and
]}We need to produce JSON with translations array. The current cue is [580] he can't sleepand. We need to translate into Simplified Chinese. The translation should be natural, maybe
he feels tremendous sadness, even though he's avenged the death of Patroclus.
他在...
And the reason why is, in his heart, Achilles knows
...
he was the one responsible for killing Patroclus, right?
Because if he didn't get into the stupid fight with Agamemnon, and
]}We need to translate cue [584]
if he did not refuse the Greeks when they requested help, then Patroclus wouldn't have died.
]}We need to produce translation for cue [585]. The sentence:
So it's because Achilles was so stubborn and so proud
that his friend Patroclus died.
that his friendPatroclus died.
So he feels tremendous guilt
...
for what happened.
And his guilt turns into an intense hatred for Hector.
And his guilt turns into anintense hatred for Hector.
That's why he's torturing Hector's body.
...
Then what happens is Priam, King Priam,
翻译成中文
who can't sleep either because his son is being tortured, okay?
谁也睡不着，因为他儿子被折腾，好的？
His son is dead, but his soul is still being tortured by Achilles.
他的儿子已死，且可算是个回到回去的回去？
He sneaks into Achilles' tent, okay?
他在前面?
And he's right behind Achilles while Achilles is talking to his generals.
...
And at this point, remember, Achilles doesn't see him.
在此时，记得，阿基琼不见他。
He's standing behind Achilles. He can take his knife and stab Achilles' head.
他在前面?
He can stab Achilles' neck, right? And that's what most people would do.
他可以在咬咬?
But Priam doesn't do that.
...
Priam instead kneels down and
Pri … ???
kisses the hand of Achilles,
?
which forces Achilles
...??????????????????????????????????????
to be in awe of this king
...????..??..??..????..?????..??..???
who has knelt down before him.
...????????????????????????????????????
And he admires Priam's courage
...??????..??..??..?????..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..???
and love for his son so much
...??..??..??..?????..??..??..??..??..??...??..??..??..??..??....??...??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..??..???
that he feels tremendous shame and
他感到巨大的羞愧与……
remorse for what he's done to Hector.
...
And he returns Hector's body to Priam as compensation.
And that's how the Iliad ends, okay?
好的，接着说：第六百一十一条：...
The main message of the Iliad is it's not war that creates civilization.
好的，接着说：第六百一十二条：...
It is love that creates civilization.
好的，接着说：...
It is Priam's love for Hector
它是普里亚姆对赫克托的爱使得他在战斗中能胜利
that gives him the courage to defeat Achilles,
它是普里亚姆的...
in battle.
...
And in this defeat, Achilles becomes a better person
???
because he's able to forgive himself and
]}
he's able to do what is right and just
. .. …… … We need to translate cues 617-619 into Simplified Chinese. Provide array translations in order. Each string may contain at most one newline. Let's translate: 617:
and return Hector to his father, okay?
...】】】】】】??…
That's the Iliad. As you can imagine,
...????…
this is extremely complicated psychology.
...…
And it forces you to think deeply about who we are as humans, okay?
...??...
Okay? Okay?
...??..???
Does that make sense? And the third thing that
...???
is shocking about the Iliad is the use of metaphors.
惊人的是《伊利亚特》使用了大量隐喻。
So what are metaphors?
那又是什么？
Metaphors are connections between things that were unseen, okay?
隐喻是把两件事物相连的方式。
So for example, if I say, the sky is a snail.
比如说，我把天空当成蜗牛。
You're like, oh, I didn't know that.
你会说：好，没想到！
I didn't know that. Okay? Do you understand? That's what a metaphor is.
我也没说过这点，先说好！
A metaphor is connecting two things that before were not connected.
一个词语把两件事物相连，之前未曾相连。
If you think about it, what this is is a new thought.
若想一想，能把此事物与之相连。
And there are lots of metaphors in the Iliad, okay?
在此句中有多种类句式。”
So essentially,
所以本质上，
metaphors teach you how to think, okay?
隐喻教你如何思考，好的？
They are the tools for thought.
它们是思考的工具。
So these are the three distinct characteristics of the Iliad
译文1
that make it unique in the world, okay?
译文2
It's switching perspectives all the time, which
译译3
creates empathy, right?
创建了共情，没错？
It talks about human psychology all the time, which creates imagination.
它在一整段时间里说着人类心理学，形成了想象力。
And it uses metaphors, which
而且…
enables you to think much more deeply about the world, okay?
使得你能更深入地思考世界，好的？
If you put these three things together,
...
what this is, ultimately, is
a theory of human, okay?
一个关于人的理论，好的？
It's a theory of what it means to be a human being.
它是关于人类的一个理论。
Before, we thought human beings fought over land.
之前我们以为人类的先前。
They fought over a woman, like Helen, okay?
...
They struggled for power.
What Homer is saying is, what it means to be human is someone
...
who has empathy, imagination,
谁有同情，想象，
and the willingness to think.
...
Okay? Only if you're willing to see,
??
feel, and think, are you human?
...
This is a new theory of human
that becomes the basis
...
for Greek civilization. And
that's why the Greeks believed the founder of the civilization
...
was not a general, he was not a king,
它不是一般人，他也不是国王，
it was a poet named Homer.
它是个作家，叫作家·哈姆罗。
Okay? And it's because of the Iliad
好的？因为《伊利亚特》……
that they all read and memorized
...
and they could recite, okay?
它们可以背诵，好的？
Because, again, this is an oral culture where you're trained to have a very strong memory.
因为，重新再说一次，口语文化里，记忆力很强。
And because they memorized the Iliad,
因为他们记住了《伊利亚》！
it further transformed them as humans,
]}
okay? This is a new theory of what it means to be human.
...
And this becomes the basis for Greek civilization,
which then becomes the basis for Western civilization.
它随后成为西方文明的基础。
And it's because of these three reasons, the polis,
“归因于此三项：城邦、字母与荷马。”
the alphabet, and Homer, that
“…”。
we have Western civilization as we know it today.
我们现在拥有的西方文明。
Okay? Any questions so far?
好的，先问一句：先前的句子？
Any questions so far, guys?
先前…
All right. Now I'm going to spend some time and discuss, okay,
好的，我会花一点时间来讨论，
why is Greek civilization different from Chinese civilization?
好的，希腊文明与中文里…
Okay? And this will help you better understand
好的…
Western civilization. So the first question is,
西方文明。所以第一个问题是，
why is it that Greeks developed alphabet,
为什么希腊人会发展文字？
okay, the alphabet, and the Chinese did not develop the alphabet?
好的，文字，才不算…
Okay? And the answer is this.
好的？答案就在这里。
The answer is,
答案是，
Greece was not an isolated culture.
希腊是个非孤立的文化。
Okay? So the people who actually developed the alphabet were the Egyptians.
...
Okay? Egyptians. And the reason why is,
Egypt was constantly in contact and communication
...
with many different societies and cultures, including the Sumerians and the Greeks.
带着许多不同的社会与文化，包括苏美尔人和希腊人。
And they could adopt new practices to advance their language.
并且可采用新做法以推进其语言。
Okay? So it was the Greeks, it was the Egyptians who developed
...
the alphabet. The Phoenicians were traders.
字母表。腓尼基人是商人。
And the Phoenicians connected the Egyptian culture to everyone else.
腓尼基人把埃及文化与其他人相连。
Okay? So it was the Phoenicians who brought
好的，先说一句：...
the alphabet to the Greeks, who, because
...
they became illiterate, were looking for a new language system.
他们变成文盲，正寻找新的语言体系。
Okay? Does that make sense? That's why,
好的，...
that's how the Greeks got the alphabet.
那就是...
Again, the question is, why didn't China develop the alphabet?
再一次...
And the answer is this. China,
和答案是这样：中国在大部分历史里，和世界其他地方隔离。
for most of its history, was isolated from the rest of the world.
和答案之…
But not only was China isolated, but
但不只是中国隔离，还...
it was stable for most of its history,
??
because for most of Chinese history,
因为在中国大部分历史里，
China was run by a class of people called scholar officials.
中国由一批叫作业官的士人统治。
Right? Confucian scholars. What was their power?
对吧？孔子学士。 他们的士…
What was their secret power? It was the ability to read and write.
它们的秘密力量是什么？就是读写的能力。
That's what differentiated them from everyone else, right?
这就是它们与其他人区别的地方，没错吧？
That's what made them indispensable to the emperor.
这就是它们给皇帝的那点儿…
That's why they were so powerful.
那是因为它们很有力。
And so when you have a monopoly over literacy,
那时……
you don't want to give it up.
…
You want to increase it.
你想要增加它。
And the way they did so
而且…
is by creating a new language called classical Chinese.
...
Literally Chinese. Okay? Does that make sense?
中文的字面意思是“中文”，好吗？
That's why there was this divergence between Greece
因为………………
and China at this time.
...
Because China, literacy was monopolized by an elite
who benefited from this monopoly. And therefore,
...
they made this monopoly much more effective
by introducing a new language called classical Chinese.
通过引入一种新语言——古典汉语来实现的。
That only they could master.
仅仅仅只给他人们的那一点点的…
Okay? Does that make sense, guys?
先前……
Excuse me?
请问一下？
Because the scholar officials,
因为学士官员，
they were in charge of bureaucracy, right?
他们在负责官僚吗？
If you're running a bureaucracy, you need the ability to read and write.
如果你要管理一个官僚体系，你就需要读写能力。
You need the ability to basically
你需要把它们的…
transport information from one place to the next, right?
“我……”，…
That's through reading and writing, through literacy.
通过阅读和书写，才有了读写能力。
Does that make sense? So only they could become bureaucrats.
这就能说得通了吧？只要有此类…
Okay? So, does that make sense?
好的，…
Okay. Any more questions?
好的，...
Okay. Second question is,
OK? 这条…
why is it that Greeks had Homer
]? 1? 1?? 1?…?…?…?…?…?…?…?…? 1?…?…?…?………?………?……………………?………?……1……..???…………?…..??……..??…...???…………………………………………………………………………………
and the Chinese, we Chinese, we never had Homer?
和中国人，我们中国人，没能有过《奥德里》吗？
Okay? And again, the problem are the scholar officials.
好的，…
If you look at Confucian thought,
如果你看得很久...
there's a hierarchy in Confucian thought, right?
...
At the very top are scholar officials.
在最上层的是学士官员。
They're the most virtuous, they're the most well -educated, they're the most cultivated, okay?
在最上层的就是学士官员。
They're the best people.
它们是最好的人民。
Next to the, below the scholar officials are the farmers
农民是最好的农民？
and the artisans, right?
和工匠，没错？
Because they produce wealth for society.
因为他们为社会产生财富。
Below them are the merchants, right?
下面是商人，没错？
And then at the very bottom are who?
然后在最底层是谁？
The artists, right?
艺术家们，没错？
The poets. Now guess what, guys?
诗人。现在猜猜看，大家好？
In Greece, this was the complete opposite.
在希腊里，这一一百百…
They placed Homer
他们把荷马放在社会的最顶层。
at the very top of the society.
每个人都想成为像荷马一样的诗人，好吗？
Everyone wanted to be a poet, like Homer, okay?
Everyone wanted to be apoet, like Homer, okay?
So when Plato was writing the Republic,
译文1
he was trying to become Homer.
译文2
He was trying to become a teacher of civilization,
译句
an inspirer of civilization,
一位启发文明的先驱者，
okay? A bigot of civilization.
好吧？一位大悟者的先驱者！
That's what Plato wanted.
那就是了！
But guess what? Thucydides, when he wrote the Peloponnesian War,
但猜猜看？特鲁克里德斯在写《伯罗奔尼亚战争》时，
he was trying to do the same thing.
他又想把它写成一条??
He was trying to inspire civilization.
其后??
He was trying to inspire new ideas.
他试图激发新思想。
Because they all wanted to become Homer.
因为他们都想成为荷马。
Okay? Because they all knew Homer was the father of civilization.
好的？因为他们都知道荷马是文明之父。
And they wanted to continue his legacy.
...
And that's what made the Greeks unique in human history.
翻译1
Because only the society put poets first
翻译2
and foremost at the top.
在最上层先是……
And no other society did so, okay?
在最上层先...
In China, it was the complete opposite.
在中国，...
Because if you're a scholar official,
在...
what you're most afraid of is independent thinking, okay?
你最怕的就是独立思考，行吗？
So censorship. Censorship.
所以…
Censorship was their main role, okay?
审查是他们的主要角色，行吗？
Controlling how people thought through censorship.
控制人们的思考通过审查。
And that's why China never really produced a Homer or a great thinker.
在此处…
Okay? Does that make sense? All right?
...
And so, this is going to be strange,
而且…
but it's only because
??
Greece got destroyed at the end of the Bronze Age.
希腊在青铜时代末期被毁灭。
It became decentralized. It lived in poor.
它变成了分散的，回到回…
That they could then become a great civilization.
其…
It was only through destruction that they could have the polis,
它只有在破坏中才有了城邦，字母表，和荷马。
the alphabet, and Homer.
好的，回到…
Okay? And that's the main message of human history.
…
It's through destruction that we have innovation.
通过破坏才有了创新
And it's only through this process that
通过此时…
human beings are able to rejuvenate their society.
“…”，…
Okay? Does that make sense? Any questions?
好的？这有道理吗？还有什么问题吗？
Was this clear to you guys?
这对你们来说清楚吗？
Okay. So we'll continue in the Greeks, okay?
好的。我们继续说说古希腊的事！